[Music]
we have all sorts of detailed stats
about dying but little about the
experience of death uh for the minority
who die under the care of paliative care
teams one's death could probably be
described as good but there's a
suspicion that for the majority who die
in hospitals or nursing homes the
experience is bad and that's where most
people die in spite of widespread
preference to die at home in almost all
populations most deaths occur in
institutions and this doesn't just have
consequences for the patient but for the
bereaved caregivers as well patients
with cancer who died in an intensive
care unit or Hospital experienced more
physical and emotional distress and
worse quality of life at the end of life
and their caregivers suffered five times
the odds of suffering post traumatic
stress disorder and nearly nine times
yards of severe prolonged disabling
grief now this was an observational
study they weren't you know randomized
to die in different locations so this
doesn't prove cause and effect but
certainly raises concerns when
researchers have looked into the care of
dying patients in
hospitals it hasn't been pretty basic
interventions to maintain patients
Comfort were often not provided contact
with dying patients was minimal and the
distancing isolation worsened as death
approached for
example a 52-year-old woman with
metastatic cancer spread to her liver
she had gross abdominal distension was
jaist and very breathless but alert her
eyes were swollen and she shed yellow
tears the patient received no care from
the nurses delegated to give care yet in
the nursing record it was recorded that
attention had been given given to her
personal hygiene and pressure areas to
prevent bed Source or hygiene in eyes
but it was all a lie the only attention
she got was to receive a commode from a
nursing assistant contact Time totaled
six minutes over the four and a half
hours the researchers kept track in
contrast what would a good death look
like retaining control dignity privacy
pain relief you choose where you choose
how emot support respecting your wishes
saying goodbye and being able to you
know leave when it's time to go and not
have you know life prolonged pointlessly
right one's best bet for all that is
access to hospice care paliative care is
Comfort measures to relieve symptoms and
improve quality of life utilized at any
stage of serious illness whereas hospice
is just Comfort measures when Focus
shifts from curing the disease to
improving the quality of one 's last
days you know hospice is often framed as
giving up but ironically when you
compare hospice versus non-hospice
patient survival the patients in hospice
actually lived longer patients who
choose Hospice Care live on average
about a month longer than similar
patients who do not choose hospice
randomize those with Advanced lung
cancer to early paralive care and they
don't live a month longer they live two
and a half months longer I mean that's
like the survival benefit you might get
from a standard chemotherapy regimen and
in fact that's one of the ways hospice
could extend Survival by avoiding the
risk of overt treatment with chemo and
its related
toxicity there are however limits to
paliative care even under hospice where
one would assume you know excellent
paliative care there are those who
appear to unavoidably spend their last
months in uncontrollable pain and this
unbearable suffering despite our best
efforts leads to requests for ending a
patient's life prematurely although
physician assist that suicide is gaining
acceptance It's only legal in eight
states plus DC in contrast
Ved is legal throughout the
US voluntarily stopping eating and
drinking vsed can be defined as a
conscious decision to voluntarily and
deliberately choose to stop eating and
drinking with a primary intention of
hastening ing death because of the
Persistence of unacceptable suffering
I've talked about fasting to extend
one's life what about fasting to shorten
it we hear a lot about physician
assisted suicide but vsd has not gained
nearly as much attention this is
presented as perplexing since supposedly
it's relatively peaceful and comfortable
way to die but is it really how long
does it take how would you do it I'll
talk about the pros and cons and prac
iCal
implications next
[Music]